<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two sermons preach'd against immorality and profaneness The first, on January 13. 1698/9. The second, on May 3. 1700. By John Thane, M.A. and one of the prebendaries of Chester.</title>
            <author>Thane, John, 1653 or 4-1727.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64470</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T834A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201131</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825122</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825122</idno>
            <idno type="VID">29495</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64470)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29495)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2081:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two sermons preach'd against immorality and profaneness The first, on January 13. 1698/9. The second, on May 3. 1700. By John Thane, M.A. and one of the prebendaries of Chester.</title>
                  <author>Thane, John, 1653 or 4-1727.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>64 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for R. Knaplock, at the Angel and Crown in St. Paul's Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Immorality --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29495:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TWO SERMONS Preach'd againſt <hi>Immorality</hi> and <hi>Profaneneſs.</hi> The Firſt, On <hi>January</hi> 13. 1698/9. The Second, On <hi>May</hi> 3. 1700. By <hi>JOHN THANE,</hi> M. A. And one of the Prebendaries of <hi>Cheſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Knaplock,</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, 1700.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:29495:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:29495:2"/>
            <head>TWO SERMONS Preach'd againſt <hi>Immorality</hi> and <hi>Profaneneſs.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>St.</hi> JOHN xii. 26.</bibl> —<hi>If any Man ſerve me, him will my Father honour.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THeſe are the Words of our bleſſed Saviour, and they contain part of the Diſcourſe wherewith he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain'd two of his Diſciples, <hi>Andrew</hi> and <hi>Philip,</hi> who came upon a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Meſſage to him. It was now about the time, as appears from the Context, when his Sorrows began, and the Scene of his Sufferings was drawing on; from the Proſpect whereof he takes Occaſion to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form his Auditors, not only of that which
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:29495:3"/> he himſelf was about to undertake, but of that likewiſe which he did require from all that had a Mind to be his Followers, and would ingage themſelves in his Service. <hi>If any Man ſerve me, let him follow me, and where I am, there ſhall alſo my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant be: If any Man ſerve me, him will my Father honour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As if he had ſaid, <q rend="inline">I am now about to drink off that bitter Cup, which the Sins of Mankind have prepared for me; and ſince that for this very End, I came into the World, that I might lay down my Life for its ſake, let not any of my Servants grudge or think it ſtrange to tread in the ſteps of their Maſter, and to follow his Example. Many I foreſee there are who will break with me upon theſe Terms, and will refuſe to become my Diſciples and Followers; but know ye that bleſſed and only bleſſed ſhall they be, who upon the Preaching of my Goſpel ſhall come in, and believe in me, and receive my Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and ſhall yield Obedience to my Laws and Commands. Happy I ſay again ſhall it be for them, if they will learn of me, and will Practice the Rules of my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, for theſe are they whom I will own and defend, and theſe are they whom my Father alſo will honour.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Having thus briefly conſider'd the Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of the Words, I come now to raiſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:29495:3"/> ſome Obſervations from them: And they ſhall be theſe Five.</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. I ſhall inquire into the Nature and Kind of the Service which is here offer'd in the Text, <hi>If any Man ſerve me.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>II. I ſhall alſo inquire who they are that may properly be called the Servants of Chriſt.</item>
               <item>III. I ſhall ſhew the Reaſonableneſs of the Service.</item>
               <item>IV. The Neceſſity of it. And,</item>
               <item>V. And laſtly, from theſe Words of our Lord, <hi>him will my Father honour.</hi> I ſhall by way of Incouragement ſet before you that immenſe Reward which attends the ſincere Performance of it.</item>
            </list>
            <p>I. Then as to the Nature and Kind of the Service. And that will appear, if we conſider what it is, and wherein it doth conſiſt.</p>
            <p>If we inquire into the nature of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, we ſhall find it to conſiſt of theſe two Parts: <hi>Viz.</hi> A firm well-grounded Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to whatever Chriſt has reveal'd, and a ſincere actual Conformity to thoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold Obligations and Duties which he
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:29495:4"/> hath laid upon us. So that to ſerve Chriſt is briefly this, to believe what he has Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd, and to do what he hath Commanded in his Word. Whence the Conſequence is plain and undoubted, that as long as we faithfully Perform the Service, ſo long and no longer will Chriſt Own us for his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants: Which ſhould make us ſo much the more Cautious and Circumſpect in our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour towards him.</p>
            <p>But then if we conſider it as to its kind, we cannot but acknowledge it to be beſt and propereſt for us, moſt befitting us as we are Men, and are endow'd with a rational Nature: As it gives us a clearer Senſe of our frail and weak Condition, and what for lorn and miſerable Creatures Sin hath made us: As it preſents us with right No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of God and of his Worſhip, and with the plaineſt and ſureſt Directions for the Government of our ſelves: As it delivers us from the Tyranny and Bondage of Sin, and from the Power of our Luſts, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead thereof puts us into a State of Son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Freedom, under the Influence of God's Grace, and the Conduct of his Holy Spirit, whereby our Underſtandings are enlighten'd, and our Wills directed, and our Affections are brought into order. So that neither our profeſt Enemies from without, nor our treacherous Friends from within, ſhall now be able to hurt us
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:29495:4"/> without our own conſent. A farther Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of whoſe Excellence we have in the Words of S. <hi>Paul, 1. Cor. 6. 9. Know ye not that the unrighteous ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God? Be not deceived; neither Fornicators, nor Adulterers, nor Drunkards, ſhall inherit the Kingdom of God: And ſuch were ſome of you: But ye are waſhed, but ye are Sanctified, but ye are Juſtified in the Name of the Lord Jeſus, and by the Spirit of our God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Since then the Nature of Chriſt's ſervice is ſuch, ſince it is ſo Excellent in its kind, and every way ſo much for our Advantage, is it not very plain that 'tis not more our Duty, than it is our Intereſt and our Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to accept it, and live according to it: And if ſo, how inexcuſable then are thoſe, who after they have taken upon them this Service, and have vow'd Allegiance to their Lord and Maſter, do notwithſtanding riſe in Rebellion againſt him, and Affront him to his very Face. Which all ſuch moſt certainly do, who by their Actions or their Speeches, or perhaps both, diſown his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and deſpiſe his Laws, and by that means endeavour to repreſent the Son of God as a Cheat and Impoſtor.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the Men that are in the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts of Irreligion and Infidelity, which they ſerve moſt faithfully, and to the beſt of their Power: Who tho' they have wholly
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:29495:5"/> abandon'd themſelves to Vice, and have quite caſt off all Modeſty and Shame, have yet ſo much Aſſurance as to ſet up for Wits, and pretend to a more refin'd way of Converſation. Theſe are they who judge of things not as they really are, but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their own ill-grounded Sentiments and Principles, which teach them to think it mean and unbecoming, to be ty'd up to Rules, and be oblig'd to live as all ſober conſidering Men chuſe to do. It ſeems for their Part, they know better than to trouble themſelves with Religion, or the Obligations of Virtue and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality, which to ſay the Truth, they have no manner of regard or reverence for. If you inquire into theſe Men's pretences, as they are ſeldom without ſome, they will tell you they have thoroughly ſtudied the Point, and have Search'd into the Reaſon and Nature of things, and are thence clearly Convinc'd that Religion, eſpecially the Chriſtian Religion, is at beſt but <hi>a cunning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deviſed Fable.</hi> This is the Scheme which they have projected to themſelves, and by ſuch wild Notions do they ſteer and govern their Actions: And what is ſtranger yet, ſeem to deſpiſe all others that are not as wicked as themſelves. Set the <hi>Men in Black,</hi> as they in deriſion call Us, ſay whate'er they can, they are reſolv'd notwithſtanding to purſue their Pleaſures, and gratifie their
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:29495:5"/> Senſes, and will never ſtint themſelves in any thing that Nature prompts them to.</p>
            <p>And now is it not high time to give a Check to ſuch avowed and barefac'd Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety, which ſets up in defiance of God himſelf, and which ſtrikes at the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Honour and Authority in the World. This is what we are called upon to do, and there is abſolute need that it ſhould be done, and doubtleſs every good Man will contribute to the doing of it. For who can be ſilent when Religion is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted, or unconcern'd when Libertiniſm is in Faſhion and Requeſt?</p>
            <p>But as this kind of behaviour is very unaccountable, ſo it is commonly fatal in the Event, and will certainly prove ſo to the Sinners of this Nation, except they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent. Becauſe their Sins are more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking, and do carry a deeper Guilt, as being Committed againſt clearer Light, and more and greater Advantages, than are af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded to other Chriſtians: And Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour we know hath ſaid, <hi>Unto whomſoever much is given, of him ſhall much be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</hi> When therefore Men have all the Means and Opportunities, and all the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to Piety and Goodneſs that can be deſired, and yet nevertheleſs turn ſuch Miſcreants, and give ſuch Scandalous Ill Examples, it looks as if God had ſome heavy Judgment in ſtore for us, and that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:29495:6"/> we were a People devoted to Deſtruction. After that God hath ſhew'd himſelf ſo often and ſo tenderly concern'd for this our <hi>Sion,</hi> what elſe is to be expected from ſuch baſe unworthly Returns, but that he ſhould pronounce the ſame of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> that he once did of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, <hi>Iſai. 5. 4. What could have been done more to my Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard that I have not done in it? Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when I looked that it ſhould bring forth Grapes, brought it forth wild Grapes? And now go to, I will tell you what I will do to my Vineyard, I will take away the Hedge thereof, and it ſhall be eaten up, and break down the Wall thereof, and it ſhall be trod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den down: And I will lay it waſte, it ſhall not be pruned or digged, but there ſhall come up Briars and Thorns.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to return; Religion or the Service of <hi>Jeſus</hi> Chriſt doth juſtly challenge our beſt care and regard, for that it enjoyns nothing but what is highly becoming, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what our own Reaſon tells us we ought to do. It lays upon us ſtrict En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements to Holineſs and Virtue, which are Conditions abſolutely required on our part: So that whenever we depart or break off from our Duty, and enter on a contrary Courſe of Sin and Diſobedience, we become as it were Vagrants and Fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, and may very properly be ſaid to run away from our Maſter.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:29495:6"/>
            <p>Since then we have all Solemnly engaged at our Baptiſm, not only to be True and Conſtant to Chriſt's Service, but alſo to Deny our ſelves, and Hazard all for his ſake, let us reſolve to make good that our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, leſt when he ſhall come again to Judge the World, we ſhould then be found Guilty, and accordingly have Sentence paſſed on us as Renegades and Deſerters. I come now in the Second Place,</p>
            <p>II. To inquire who they are that may properly be called the Servants of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Now to make us the Servants of Chriſt two things are required.</p>
            <p>1. That we believe in Chriſt, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Love, Honour and Adore him as the Son of God, and the Saviour of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind.</p>
            <p>2. That we ſo receive all his Laws and Commands as to make them the only Rule of our Obedience and Practice.</p>
            <p>This is the Subſtance of our Duty, as we are Chriſtians, and if we are ſincere in the performance of it, and will do the beſt we can to pleaſe God, his Grace will ever be ready to aſſiſt us, and to ſupply our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects. So that now we know who and what the Servants of Chriſt are, namely, All ſuch who own Chriſt for their Lord, and in O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to his Authority ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be govern'd according to his Will and Pleaſure. This is a ſhort and plain
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:29495:7"/> Account of the Matter, and is that which every one that makes any Pretence to Chriſtianity muſt acknowledge to be true.</p>
            <p>And if what I have here ſaid be true, as certainly it is, then what a fatal miſtake are they Guilty of, who think they can ſerve Chriſt well enough, while they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in a State of Sin, and go on in a conſtant Courſe of Wickedneſs and Vice? For what a ſtrange Contradiction is this, and how is it poſſible for theſe men to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile their Belief and their Practice together? Do they imagine that Chriſt will alter the Terms of Salvation, and will account them as Servants, who are no better than Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels and Out-Laws? If Chriſt himſelf will Condemn thoſe who only call him, <hi>Lord,</hi> without ever doing the things which he hath ſaid, then what a ſevere Doom do they deſerve, who are ſo far from giving him any ſuch outward Verbal Reſpect, that they make no Scruple openly to Affront and Revile him?</p>
            <p>Bleſſed God! what a ſtrange Degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy do we now ſee in the Faith and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of moſt Chriſtians, and to what a low ebb and deſpiſed Eſtate is Chriſtianity, the beſt and moſt perfect Inſtitution, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd! That very Religion which hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeiz'd on the Hearts and Affections of Men, and preſently brought them off
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:29495:7"/> from Idols and other Heathen Fopperies, and which inſenſibly ingag'd the moſt rude, and fierce, and ſtubborn Diſpoſitions: And not only ſo, but moreover inſpir'd them with ſuch Zeal for the Truth and Purity of it, as made vaſt Numbers of its Profeſſors, chuſe to Sacrifice their Lives, rather than renounce and betray it. How is <hi>that</hi> Religion now become the Scorn of Fools, and the Sport of the Wicked and the Profane! And how are the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures vilify'd by Seducers, and the Truths therein contain'd render'd of no Account or Conſideration by them? So that all things put together, who could believe ſuch a Change as now is, did not Experience ſhew it, or even think it morally poſſible, had not our <hi>Lord</hi> himſelf foretold it?</p>
            <p>That there are too many Examples of this Kind, I need not ſay much to prove, ſince the very Complexion of the Age doth abundantly evince it.</p>
            <p>Behold then on the one hand the <hi>Theiſt,</hi> or Moral Believer, who is ſo far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Chriſtian, that he calls in Queſtion the Truth and certainty of reveal'd Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. This is a ſort of Men who pretend it ſeems to more than ordinary ſtrictneſs and reſervedneſs of Converſation, and ſo far indeed they deſerve to be commended: But then, alas! what can <hi>theſe</hi> ſignifie <hi>alone</hi> to us now, without Faith, and without a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:29495:8"/> Redeemer? Next to the <hi>Theiſt</hi> comes the bold <hi>Socinian</hi> Controvertiſt, one who laughs at the Doctrine of the Trinity, and flatly denies the Divinity of our Lord and Saviour. And tho' both Scripture and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity are plain againſt him, yet ſo highly conceited is he of his own little <hi>Reaſon,</hi> that he ſticks not to preferr it even to <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> and <hi>Couneils.</hi> This alſo is a growing Miſchief, a ſpreading Infection, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Danger it threatens is ſo much the greater: For if once Men be permitted to vent ſuch falſe and pernicious Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, what elſe is to be look'd for, but that all ſhould at laſt end in Scepticiſm, or downright Infidelity?</p>
            <p>Look again on the other hand, and ſee where the <hi>Blaſphemer</hi> appears, who not content by a lewd and debauch'd Life, to crucifie his Maſter afreſh, and put him to open ſhame, ſtrives all he can to attacque him in his Perſon, and purſues him to the very Seat of Majeſty and Glory. This is the way and the behaviour of him, who is ſaid by the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73. 9. to <hi>ſet his Mouth againſt the Heavens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With the Blaſphemer we may joyn the <hi>Profane</hi> Perſon, as being next akin to him. And here again the Scene is Diſmal enough, ſince it preſents us with nothing, but the bold Flights and Extravagancies of a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane Temper, which as it is too viſible in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:29495:8"/> of the Youth of our Nation, eſpecially thoſe who are in ſome repute for Parts and Education, ſo it is very Induſtriouſly Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagated by others, who take a pride in expoſing Religion, and drawing Men off to Infidelity and Vice. And tho' none perhaps who are Guilty in this way have Actually renounc'd Chriſtianity, yet they appear on all Occaſions with ſuch an Air of Lightneſs, and are ſo mightily addicted to this abominable kind of Railery, that neither God himſelf, nor his Son <hi>Jeſus</hi> Chriſt, nor any the moſt Serious and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred things can eſcape them. This is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Evil that ought ſpeedily to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medied, elſe the Contagion will ſpread amain.</p>
            <p>Next to theſe ſtands the <hi>common and Profane Swearer,</hi> one indeed who is much better known to us, as coming oftner in our way, and meeting us almoſt where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever we go. This, alas, is become ſo common and ſo reigning a Vice, and which hath ſpread it ſelf ſo wide, and hath got ſuch mighty Numbers on its ſide, that 'tis much to be fear'd it will not ſo eaſily be rooted out. However, we may ſtill hope to put a ſtop to it in ſome meaſure, if fit and proper Remedies be duly apply'd. 'Tis true, the meaner ſort of People are generally tainted with this Evil, but then none can ſo effectually cure it in them as
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:29495:9"/> the Magiſtrate. As for thoſe of Quality and Condition, 'tis to be hop'd that a little Conſideration will ſhew them the Odiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Sillineſs of this Vice, and will let them ſee how Contrary this Cuſtom is to good Senſe and good Breeding, and will likewiſe convince them that it is altogether as unbecoming the <hi>Gentleman</hi> as the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</hi> Such commonly have great Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages above Ignorant Inferior People, and conſequently would they but conſider, as it becomes them to do, the <hi>Being</hi> and <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> of God, if they have any Senſe at all of Religion, they cannot but own that the Divine Majeſty is highly affronted, while they make thus bold with his Name upon every vain and trifling Occaſion.</p>
            <p>Much more I confeſs might be ſaid to expoſe this horrid Crime, which is become ſo very rife not only in this, but in moſt other Countries, eſpecially where the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh</hi> Religion prevails, but I forbear, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I would not be tedious.</p>
            <p>There are two ſorts of Sinners ſtill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, <hi>The Intemperate</hi> and the <hi>Laſcivious:</hi> I have choſen to mention theſe both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, becauſe tho' they may ſometimes act ſingly and apart, yet they very often meet in one and the ſame Perſon. For when by Drinking over-much, or as <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>'s Expreſſion is, by <hi>Tarrying long at the Wine,</hi> the Head is intoxicated, and the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:29495:9"/> Blood inflam'd, then Luſt ſeizes the Man, and the brutiſh Appetite prevails, And here I cannot but obſerve, that as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable as theſe Vices are in themſelves, and as un becoming the Faith and Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Chriſtianity, they have never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs been a long while in Vogue and Repute amongſt us, and the Frequency of the Commiſſion ſeems in part to have leſſen'd the Reproach which is juſtly due to them. For what more common than for the Drunkard to paſs only for a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Companion, or for an honeſt and good-natur'd Fellow, one that does no Body any harm, and the like? And then again as to the Lewd Perſon, how or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary a thing is it to hear him cry'd up for a fine Gentleman, and a Wit, and a Man of Intrigue? All which in the Cant of Libertines paſs for Titles of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and ſeem to denote the beſt and higheſt Accompliſhments.</p>
            <p>Thus have theſe two Excellent Virtues, <hi>Temperance</hi> and <hi>Chaſtity,</hi> which do ſo properly belong to Chriſtians, been in a manner diſcountenanc'd chiefly by the Force and Power of Example. But for all that, Intemperance and Uncleanneſs are Sins ſtill, and ſuch Sins as will finally ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude Men from the Kingdom of Heaven. God no doubt intended by the Laws and Religion of his Son to reſtrain Men from
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:29495:10"/> all manner of Senſuality, eſpecially thoſe groſs Exceſſes and Impurities, to which the <hi>Gentiles</hi> had univerſally addicted themſelves: And accordingly God is ſaid by the Apoſtle <hi>to have called us not unto Uncleanneſs, but unto Holineſs, 1 Theſſ.</hi> 4. 7. Thus St. <hi>Peter</hi> alſo warns the new Converts, <hi>To live no longer in the Fleſh, to the Luſts of Men, but to the Will of God, 1 Pet.</hi> 4. 2. This is the Evidence which the Scripture gives us, and if we believe it to be true, nothing can be plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner than that the Practice of theſe Sins, as harmleſs as ſome may think them, is enough to endanger their Salvation.</p>
            <p>Nay, if we conſider theſe Men with reſpect to this World, what would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of theſe faſhionable Sinners, were St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Rule once put in Practice? <hi>If any Man,</hi> ſays he, <hi>that is called a Brother,</hi> that is, a Chriſtian, <hi>be a Fornicator, or a Drunkard, with ſuch a one, no not to eat, 1 Cor.</hi> 5. 11. How would ſuch an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction as this ſhock moſt of the fine Wits and Gallants of our Days? The Apoſtle, 'tis true, did give this Advice, or rather Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, to the Chriſtians at <hi>Corinth,</hi> which was as looſe and debauch'd a Place as any at that time; but ſtill I much que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion whether ſuch Diſcipline could be practiſed among us <hi>now.</hi> And yet 'twere but reaſonable in my Opinion that ſome
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:29495:10"/> kind of Diſgrace ſhould be fix upon them by Publick Authority, and that for the ſake and out of reſpect to Religion, which can never have that Influence upon Men which it ought to have, while ſuch Crimes as theſe are conniv'd at and ſuffer'd to go unpuniſh'd.</p>
            <p>I am ſenſible that a great deal more might be ſaid upon theſe Heads, but I fear I have almoſt tir'd your Patience in thus repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting the Blemiſhes and Deformities of Humane Nature: But you will pardon me, ſince I had no other Deſign in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing them, but only in order to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and reform them.</p>
            <p>And that we may effectually do ſo, what other or better courſe can we take than to conſult our own Reaſon, which will eaſily diſcover to us the infinite Scandal as well as Danger of ſuch Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices, which are ſo odious to God, and ſo deteſtable among all wiſe and good Men. This will teach us rightly to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare things, and make a true judgment of them, and will plainly Demonſtrate to us, that to live Virtuouſly, is indeed to live wiſely, and like Men, and according to the Dignity of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: That if we would in good earneſt approve our ſelves the Servants of Chriſt, and do all thoſe things which he hath commanded, what an agreeable and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:29495:11"/> Change there would ſuddenly appear in the World. The truth is, we may eaſily deceive and abuſe our ſelves; but when all is ſaid, we muſt either be Chriſt's Servants, or the Devil's Slaves, either the Laws of Chriſt muſt rule and govern us, or elſe Sin will have the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion over us: According to that Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſm Iſpoken by our Saviour to the <hi>Jews, Whoſoever committeth Sin, is the Servant of Sin, John</hi> 8. 34. And St. <hi>Paul</hi> is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe very expreſs to the ſame purpoſe: <hi>Know ye not, that to whomſoever ye yield your ſelves ſervants to obey, his Servants ye are to whom ye obey, whether of Sin unto Death, or of Obedience unto Righteouſneſs, Rom.</hi> 6. 16. Which brings me to the <hi>Third</hi> Thing I obſerv'd from the Words, and that is the Reaſonableneſs of the Service.</p>
            <p>III. Had Chriſtianity nothing beſide the Authority of its Founder, to recommend and inforce the Practice of it, even that alone were ſufficient of it ſelf. Haſt Thou ſaid then, O Bleſſed <hi>Jeſu, if any Man ſerve me, him will my Father honour,</hi> and can any Man deny to ſerve Thee? Haſt Thou moreover done and ſuffer'd ſo very much for the wretched Sons of Men, and will any of them refuſe to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come obedient to thy Will? Nay, haſt Thou aſcertain'd ſo ample a Reward upon
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:29495:11"/> thy Word and Promiſe, and will not every one gladly accept this ſo kind, this ſo gracious an Overture?</p>
            <p>No; Thouſands ſtill there are who will not be perſuaded for all that, who will not underſtand their true Intereſt, but rather chuſe to make themſelves Slaves, than to live as the Sons of God, and Freemen of Chriſt. Stupid and ungrateful Sinner! What hath bewitch'd thee into this Treachery and Diſobedience to the beſt of Maſters? How canſt thou anſwer theſe thy Doings even to thy own Ingenuity and Conſcience? Doſt thou imagine thou ſhalt find thy Account ſooner or better in ſerving thy own Luſts, and gratifying thy unreaſonable and unlawful Deſires, than in keeping the Laws of God, and obeying his moſt juſt and reaſonable Commands? If thou art really of this Mind, know then that thy Caſe is deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate, ſince thou art not like to be undeceiv'd, till it be too late for thee to return and repent.</p>
            <p>'Tis true indeed, Chriſt hath invited us all into his Service, but then he juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expects that whoever will become his Servants, ſhould ſtrictly obſerve the Rules and Orders of his Houſe: Which is no more than what is commonly pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed, and thought to be very reaſonable among Men. Which Rules of his no
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:29495:12"/> one amongſt us can be ignorant of but by his own Fault: For the Word of Truth lyes open to all, and every one may ſee and learn from thence what he is par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly oblig'd unto. Let none of us therefore ſcruple or boggle at any thing that Chriſt hath thought fit to command us: Let us not ſtand upon Terms with our Lord, nor expect that we ſhould pick and chuſe our own Work: Beſure ſo wiſe a Maſter would require nothing of his Servants, but what is fit to be done by them; nothing but what is certainly very good and proper, and even neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for us in all Conditions: So that if after all his Kindneſs to us, we are ſtill wilful and perverſe, and are reſolv'd to ſerve our Luſts, and to continue in our Sins, what can in reaſon be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, but that we ſhould be turn'd out of our Service, and immediately be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd over to the power of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil?</p>
            <p>But I am willing to hope <hi>better things of you</hi> all, <hi>and things that accompany ſalvation,</hi> becauſe there is ſo much Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for it; becauſe there is ſuch Agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs and Satisfaction in the Practice of Religion and Virtue. Which makes me wonder the more how it comes to paſs, that Men otherwiſe of very good Senſe and Underſtanding, and who have had
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:29495:12"/> all the Advantages of an ingenious and liberal Education, ſhould after ſuch fair and promiſing beginnings turn errant De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchees, and thereby defeat all the Hopes which their Relations, or Friends, or Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, might conceive of them. But Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is juſtified of her Children, and Religion will always approve it ſelf to the judicious and ſober part of Mankind: The Nature of whoſe Service is ſuch, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever our Circumſtances are in the World, if we would diſtinguiſh our ſelves, and excel in any degree, we cannot poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly miſs of our Aim, ſo long as we keep conſtant to our Rule.</p>
            <p>IV. The <hi>Fourth</hi> Thing to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd is the Neceſſity of the Service.</p>
            <p>There is undoubtedly a Neceſſity laid upon us all of being Good, and Virtuous, and Holy, and no Pretence whatſoever has Power to take off the Obligation: Tho' ſome perhaps will be apt to ſay, They cannot leave off this or that parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Sin: They have try'd as they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, and have done whatever they could, but it ſeems all in vain: The reaſon is, they have indulg'd themſelves ſo long in the Practice of Sin, that it is become in a manner natural to them, ſo that they hardly perceive when they commit it. Thus it too often happens in the caſe of profane Swearing and Curſing. Again,</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:29495:13"/>
            <p>Another perhaps will tell you, for his part he is very ſenſible that Intemperance is a great Sin, but for all that he is not able to reſiſt the Charms of Wine and good Company; beſides that, he has been ſo long and ſo deeply ingag'd in this way, and has contracted ſuch and ſo many Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, that he knows not how to get fairly off: The Man perhaps is not ſo much ſatisfied in what he does, as unwilling to thwart his corrupt Inclination.</p>
            <p>The lewd Perſon no doubt has his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences too as well as the former, but theſe are for the moſt part ſuch as are not ſo fit to be mention'd.</p>
            <p>Now the Caſe of theſe Men is certainly very bad, and their Condition is highly deplorable, and that becauſe they trifle and are unconcern'd about the main Iſſue, and have not that inward affecting Senſe of the Danger which they ought to have. Were they once made ſenſible of that, they would quickly forego their vicious Practices; but then here lyes the Difficulty, that when Men's Impieties have proceeded thus far, the Commands of God's Word, and the Terrors and Threatnings of the Goſpel, are too gentle an Application for the Cure of them: And therefore ſome more effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual Methods are to be taken, ſuch as may thoroughly awaken Sinners, and may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince them of their Wickedneſs and Folly,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:29495:13"/> and ingage them to become Modeſt and Temperate, Sober and Religious, or at leaſt reſtrain them from breaking out into open Lewdneſs and Debauchery.</p>
            <p>Tis therefore a very proper Remedy which <hi>Solomon</hi> preſcribes, <hi>a Rod for the Fool's Back;</hi> 'tis ſeaſonable doubtleſs and uſeful too in this Caſe: For when Men are ſo bent upon Wickedneſs that they will not grow better by Reproof, 'tis requiſite ſome kind of Diſcipline ſhould be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed upon them: When they are ſo har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den'd in Sin that neither Religion nor Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon will reduce them, they ſhould then be made to feel the Cenſure of the Law. This is the moſt likely Method of effecting that Work, which Charity as well as Prudence requires to be done: And the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a little Severity, when rational Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives and Perſuaſives fail, is the trueſt ſort of Kindneſs that can be ſhew'd to ſuch Men: Who, if they are let alone in their Extravagancies, will ſoon grow Heady and Licentious, and will not be ſtopp'd in their Career, till at laſt they <hi>give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves over unto Laſciviouſneſs, to work all Uncleanneſs with Greedineſs, Epheſ.</hi> 4. 19.</p>
            <p>The Truth is, when I conſider the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances we are in, as to the abounding of Vice and Immorality, it cannot but ſeem ſtrange that it ſhould be ſo: That Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:29495:14"/> which is the chief Intereſt and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of Mankind, ſhould be ſo little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded as it is in the World: That Virtue ſhould be ſo much diſcountenanc'd, and Sobriety and Temperance ſo rarely ſeen: That Men ſhould thus proſtitute their Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and affront and baffle their Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and at the ſame time ſhould va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue themſelves upon ſuch Management as this: This, I ſay, could not but ſeem very ſtrange, were it not that <hi>the God of this World, 2 Cor.</hi> 4. 4. whom they have ſo faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſerv'd, <hi>hath blinded</hi> the Eyes of <hi>their Mind,</hi> and will not ſuffer <hi>the Light</hi> of Truth to <hi>ſhine</hi> clearly <hi>unto them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But however that be, this is certain, that if they who are Chriſtians will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mean themſelves as the Servants of Chriſt, if they will not conſider and actually re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to their Duty, periſh they muſt, there is no help for it: For when they have ſaid all they can for themſelves, God, who knows their Hearts, and what Means and Opportunities they have had, but have neglected, will infallibly puniſh every wilful and impenitent Sinner accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Deſert. I might inlarge upon this Head, but it is time now to turn my ſelf the other way, and to ſhew in the Fifth and Laſt Place.</p>
            <p>V. That immenſe Reward which at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends the ſincere Performance of our Duty.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:29495:14"/>
            <p>
               <hi>If any Man ſerve me,</hi> ſays <hi>Chriſt, him will my Father honour.</hi> Bleſſed Lord! What abundant Encouragement is here given to thy faithful Servants and Followers from theſe comfortable Words of Thine? Haſt Thou ſaid this, O Gracious Maſter, and will not all thoſe who profeſs thy Faith and Religion, be eagerly ambitious of this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour? Will any that have ſo vaſt a Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence in view and proſpect, chuſe to ſeek and follow after any other? Or think it worth their while to make their Court here below, to theſe fading Honours, theſe tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd Glories, which the Men of this World ſo much admire? Silly miſtaken Creatures! What is there in any, nay, in all of them, that ſhould tempt us from our Maſter's Service, only for the ſake of a few vain, empty and inſignificant Titles? Did we but rightly know our ſelves, and underſtand our beſt Intereſt, we ſhould deſpiſe theſe gaudy Trifles, and ſhould quite diſreliſh the groſſer Delights and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactions of Senſe: We ſhould then mind Religion and the weighty Concernments of it, and ſhould make theſe the main Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit and Endeavour of our Lives: We ſhould fix our Thoughts and our Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions chiefly on things above, and ſhould be continually wiſhing for and aſpiring after thoſe invaluable Rewards, thoſe Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Honours, <hi>which eye hath not ſeen,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:29495:15"/> nor ear heard, neither have enter'd into the Heart of Man to conceive.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe indeed are the proper Recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of our Fidelity and Conſtancy, and they are the higheſt and nobleſt that our Nature is capable of: And tho' theſe in the main are future only, and in reverſion, yet Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion uſually gives us ſomething in Hand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide; and that is the preſent Payment which every one that Lives well, doth one way or other receive.</p>
            <p>The World, 'tis time, is generally very bad, and the Wicked are by much the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Number, however Virtue and true Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs do very ſeldom fail of Reſpect even among thoſe. But ſuppoſe the worſt to happen that can, and that Wickedneſs ſhould every where prevail, and Impiety get the upper hand, ſtill the faithful and ſincere Chriſtian is ſure to be taken care of however; our Lord hath promiſed it, and we have good reaſon to depend upon his Word; for he is a great Prince, and one that hath all Power at command, and ſo is continually in readineſs, whenever he pleaſes, to right and vindicate his diſtreſs'd Servants. But if after all we ſhould ſuffer a while here, let none of us be diſcourag'd thereat, ſince Chriſt hath Honours and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments enough to beſtow upon all that ſhall ſuffer in his Cauſe, and upon his Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:29495:15"/>
            <p>This is a very incouraging Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to us all, and which ought to animate our Hopes, and excite our Ambition, not after earthly Honours and Advantages, which too often betray us, but after thoſe bright and dazling Crowns, which are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd in Heaven for us. 'Tis the want of a right apprehenſion of theſe Matters, that makes us ſo indifferent about our beſt and weightieſt Concernments: Did we but know how to value theſe as we ought, we ſhould purſue them with far more Zeal and Earneſtneſs than we commonly do. And O that we were all of us ſo wiſe as to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand our own Happineſs, and would effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually be perſuaded to <hi>ſeek the Honour that cometh from God only, John</hi> 5. 44. For 'tis certain none but that can ſtand us in ſtead, none but that can make us truly ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable.</p>
            <p>And therefore whatever befalls us here, let us always appear on the ſide of Religion, and let us endeavour to reſcue it from the exceptions and cavils of unreaſonable Men: And ſo much the more, becauſe whenever that is attacqu'd or injur'd, the Honour of our Great Maker is then concern'd, which we muſt be ſure to vindicate, or muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to be diſown'd and diſcarded by him. The Words which our Saviour ſpake to this Purpoſe are very remarkable, <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhall be aſhamed of me, and of my
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:29495:16"/> Words, in this Adulterous and Sinful Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, of him alſo ſhall the Son of Man be aſhamed, when he cometh in the Glory of his Father with the holy Angels, Mar.</hi> 8. 38. This is a terrible Sentence indeed, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ſhould do well to conſider how far any of us may be concern'd in it: Whether at this very day, even <hi>in this adulterous and ſinful generation,</hi> when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we hear the Son of God revil'd in his Perſon, or ridicul'd and evil ſpoken of in his Laws and Doctrine, if we are ſilent and paſſive on ſuch an occaſion, he may not then juſtly reckon us as <hi>aſham'd of him and of his Words?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Sum of all is this: If we will own Chriſt for our Maſter, we muſt then ſerve him to the utmoſt of our Power; we muſt eſpouſe his Intereſt, and maintain his Cauſe againſt all Oppoſers whatſoever, againſt the <hi>Theiſt,</hi> and the <hi>Unitarian,</hi> the <hi>Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> and the <hi>profane Perſon,</hi> againſt the <hi>Common Swearer,</hi> the <hi>Drunkard,</hi> and the <hi>Laſcivious:</hi> All which are one way or other, either in Principle or in Practice, the avowed Adverſaries of Chriſt, and of the true Chriſtian Faith and Religion. This, if we conſider, is as little as any of us can do, ſo long as we profeſs our ſelves Servants to the Bleſſed <hi>Jeſus,</hi> all whoſe Commands ought to be dearer to us than our very Lives.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:29495:16"/>
            <p>And ſince Chriſt our Lord hath ſtrictly charg'd all Men, of all ſorts and degrees, without Exception, to ſhun the Ways of Sin, and the Paths of Iniquity, let us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt this Matter with our ſelves, and with all our might ſtrive againſt the force and bent of our evil Inclinations and Paſſions. Whatever Difficulty there may be in the Attempt, ſtill Duty and Obligation ought to take place here. Let us not take upon us to diſpute or cavil at any of his Commands, but let us readily comply with them all whatever they be, and be thoroughly ſatisfied that it is our Intereſt, as well as Duty, to fulfil and obey them.</p>
            <p>Let us not think any thing too hard or too dear to part with for his Sake, who hath ſhew'd himſelf the beſt Friend and the greateſt Benefactor to Mankind that ever was. And ſo much the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in return to thoſe manifold unſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Advantages which he hath procured to us, all that he expects or requires from us, is, that we conſtantly maintain and practice his excellent Religion, whatever Contempt or Hardſhip we may meet with from the World.</p>
            <p>In a word: Tho' Vice and Profaneneſs have got many powerful Advocates on their ſide, yet let not that be any diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to us while we have Chriſt on ours. The Cauſe which we undertake is in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:29495:17"/> it ſelf highly honourable, and at this Jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture the moſt neceſſary of all other. The things that we contend for are Truth, Virtue and Religion, the beſt, the moſt valuable in themſelves, and the moſt deſerving of our Zeal and Concern. Chriſt is our Maſter and Lord, and as his Servants we appear, we ſtrive, we oppoſe: Letus be found true to his Service, juſt to his Intereſt, and zealous for his Honour, and then that God who hath ſaid, <hi>them that honour me I will honour,</hi> ſhall tranſlate us into his own moſt Glorious Kingdom, and ſhall actually Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and Honour us to all Eternity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Almighty and Merciful God, of whoſe only Gift it cometh, that thy faithful People do unto thee true and laudable Service: Grant, we beſeech thee, that we may ſo faithfully ſerve thee in this Life, that we fail not finally to attain thy heavenly Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, through the Merits of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>our Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:29495:17"/>
            <head>A SECOND SERMON Preach'd againſt <hi>Immorality</hi> and <hi>Profaneneſs.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>DEUT. xxxii. 6.</bibl> Do ye thus requite the Lord, O Fooliſh People and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwiſe?—</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THeſe Words are part of that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetick Song which <hi>Moſes</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and which he tells us he <hi>ſpake in the Ears of all the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of Iſrael.</hi> Here in a kind of Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Strain he ſets forth the Goodneſs of God, and the Perverſeneſs and Diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the People: And being ſhortly to leave the World, he Summons them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and rehearſes this Song for a Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony againſt them, if ſo be they ſhould
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:29495:18"/> hereafter turn aſide and forget their God, as he foreſaw they would.</p>
            <p>Alas, ſo very deceitful is the Heart of Man, ſo prone to Evil, and ſo averſe from Good, that the wiſeſt and beſt Inſtructions can make but little Impreſſion upon it: Tho' <hi>Moſes</hi> here ſaith, <hi>my Doctrine ſhall drop as the Rain, my Spirit ſhall diſtil as the Dew,</hi> yet from ſo corrupt a Root, ſo cold and barren a Soil, ſcarce any fruit or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe was to be hop'd, for ſuch was the unhappy Temper of that People, ſo weak their Judgment, and ſo perverſe their Will, that the Prophet ſeems to give them up for loſt. <hi>They are,</hi> ſays he, <hi>a Nation void of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel; neither is there any Underſtanding them,</hi> ver. 28.</p>
            <p>And indeed what Wiſdom, or Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, or Counſel, can any People or Nation be ſaid to have, when once they have caſt off God and Religion, and are ſunk into all manner of Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Vice? That is a ſad and deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Caſe indeed, and which will bring ſwift inevitable Ruin upon us, if we do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>think our ſelves in time, and return to a wiſer and better Mind. Which is the beſt thing that we can do, and the only certain way for us to eſcape the Danger? Whereas while we are thus Unmindful of <hi>the Rock that begat us,</hi> and do thus <hi>forget God that form'd us,</hi> we have reaſon to expect that he
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:29495:18"/> will rub up our Memories, and will, to our coſt, make us feel the weight of that Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure which we refuſed to ſtand in awe of.</p>
            <p>I ſay we have all juſt cauſe to fear that, becauſe as this kind of behaviour is the worſt ſort of Ingratitude, ſo it is moreover a very high Diſhonour to God, and a down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Contempt of his Majeſty and Laws. And <hi>do ye thus requite the Lord, O Fooliſh People and Unwiſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In diſcourſing upon which Words I ſhall endeavour to make out theſe <hi>Four things.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>I. The Baſeneſs and Ingratitude of a Sinful and Irreligious Courſe of Life.</item>
               <item>II. The groſs Abſurdity and Unaccoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Folly of ſuch a Courſe.</item>
               <item>III. The evil Conſequences which at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it with reſpect to Men's private Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts and Concerns.</item>
               <item>IVly, and Laſtly, As it is Deſtructive of the Welfare and Proſperity of any Nation or People.</item>
            </list>
            <p>I. The Baſeneſs and Ingratitude of a Sinful and Irreligious Courſe of Life.</p>
            <p>The Obligations we lye under to God are Certain and Unqueſtionable, whether we take the light of Nature, or the brigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Diſcoveries of Revelation for our Rule and Guide. Either of which doth plainly ſhew Impiety to be Baſeneſs and Diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:29495:19"/> the utmoſt Ingratitude. Thus ſeveral of the Heathens, tho' they had only the dim light of Reaſon to direct them, could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs diſcover the neceſſity of Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Will of God: Which made one of them to ſay, <hi>Virtue, Philoſophy and Juſtice, are but the ſound of empty Words, 'tis only a good Life that can make Men Happy, Sen. Ep.</hi> 123. But then as for Revelation, that indeed hath made our Duty, and the ſeveral Obligations of it, ſo plain, that Men muſt be utter Infidels if they reject it. So that upon either of theſe Accounts no pretence of Ignorance what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever can excuſe Men for their Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dience or Unbelief. For as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith in the Words immediately after the Text <hi>Is not he thy Father that hath bought thee? Hath not he made thee, and eſtabliſh'd thee?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed whoever conſiders God un<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der the Notion of a Father, hath all the reaſon in the World to honour and obey him: Becauſe for any one to call him ſo what is it but at the ſame time and in the ſame words to acknowledge him as the Author of his Being, the Preſerver of his Life, and the Founder of all his Happineſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I ſhall therefore conſider God in theſe three Reſpects, any of which doth exact from us all poſſible Obedience and Service. And,</p>
            <p>1. As he is the Author of our Beings.</p>
            <p>Did we not Live in an Age that call<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:29495:19"/> every thing, how certain ſoever, in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, it might ſeem needleſs to Vindicate the truth of this Propoſition: But ſince Infidelity is become a ſort of Profeſſion, and Atheiſm begins to gain Proſelytes amongſt us, 'tis ſurely high time to appear for God, and to aſſert his Being and Sovereignty over the Sons of Men. And the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wicked Men have been, and ſtill are very Induſtrious in corrupting the Minds of unwary People: The Poyſon hath been long prepar'd and diſperſed abroad in Books and Pamphlets, and the ill Effects it hath produc'd are viſible in the Lives and Manners of too many amongſt us. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver perhaps in any Age did Sin and Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs more generally abound; at beſt never was leſs Zeal ſhewn in the Exerciſe of Devotion, and all other inſtances of Piety and Religion, than in theſe unhappy Days of ours. And yet when I have ſaid this, it can't however but ſeem very ſtrange, that in a Nation where Chriſtianity is truly profeſs'd, there ſhould any be found ſo deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perately wicked as to diſown their Maker: Becauſe to do that is a moſt flagrant Crime, 'tis the very height of Impiety, and Men muſt firſt abandon their Reaſon before they can arrive at it.</p>
            <p>Since it is God therefore that hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow'd a Being upon us, ſince <hi>it is he that hath made us, and not we our ſelves,</hi> ſhall
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:29495:20"/> we be ſo highly Diſingenuous, ſo heinouſly Ungrateful, as to diſhonour at leaſt, if not deny him, by the open looſeneſs and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſneſs of our Lives? Suffer me a little to expoſtulate the Matter, not to upbraid but to convince you. Is God our Father, and can we find in our Hearts to carry it thus undutifully towards him, and ſeem at leaſt by our Actions, as if we had a mind to caſt him off, and diſown all kind of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to him, and Dependance upon him? Again, hath God made us only that we ſhould ſerve and enjoy him, and to that End hath given us a reaſonable immortal Soul, and ſeveral excellent Faculties and Endowments, whereby we are enabled to do him Homage, and ſhall we, ungrateful Creatures as we are, employ theſe Gifts of his, upon the very worſt things, in the gratification of our Luſts, in the ſervice of our Sins and Follies, in the diſcountenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of Virtue, and in neglecting or deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing every thing that is Commendable and Praiſe-worthy? This muſt needs be a great Reproach to us as we are Men; and had we any the leaſt ſenſe of Duty or Gratitude, we could not but inwardly abhorr and condemn our ſelves for it. 'Tis true, we may flatter our ſelves now, and think whatever we pleaſe, but we ſhall aſſuredly find at one time or other, that this kind of behaviour is the higheſt Indignity, the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:29495:20"/> baſeſt Ingratitude that we can poſſibly be Guilty of.</p>
            <p>But then as God is our Maker; ſo,</p>
            <p>2. Is he our Preſerver alſo. As God of his Goodneſs firſt brought us into Being, ſo doth he by his Providence ſtill continue the ſame unto us: For that according to the Apoſtle he <hi>upholdeth all things by the Word of his Power, Heb.</hi> 1. 3. And not only ſo, but as we are his Creatures, he is graciouſly pleaſed to provide for us, and freely to diſpence to us not the Neceſſaries of Life only, but the Comforts and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies of it too. He it is that takes care of us and our Concerns, and that keeps us in all our ways: 'Tis his good Providence that Watches over us, and that Defends and Guards us in all Dangers. 'Tis his Bleſſing that conſtantly brings us in Proviſion, and ſupplies our Store, and that makes <hi>our Corn, and our Wine, and our Oyl to increaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe and ſuch like are the good things which come down from above, and which we may make a right and proper Uſe of, if we pleaſe. But, alas, 'tis ſo far from that, that altho' God be thus Kind and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgent to us, yet how Ill is he ſerv'd by too many of us? How perverſe commonly is our behaviour towards him, and what a wretched requital do we make him for thoſe many Favours and Bleſſings which
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:29495:21"/> we receive? Nay, tho' they are all his Gifts that we ſubſiſt upon, yet for the moſt part ſo diſingenuous are we as to miſemploy and abuſe them.</p>
            <p>Thus in times of Proſperity, when by the divine Providence we are made Rich, how apt are we to forget or ſlight our great Benefactor, and upon our <hi>being full to deny him, and ſay, who is the Lord? Prov.</hi> 30. 9. When we are in Poſſeſſion of all that our Hearts can wiſh, inſtead of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging his Kindneſs as we ought, we preſently grow either Covetous, or Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual, and are ſo far from uſing what we have to the beſt Advantage, that is, to the Glory of God, and the Relief and Benefit of others, that perhaps we will not uſe it at all; or if we do, 'tis chiefly in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of our Luſts and Vices. 'Tis with theſe his Enemies that we take part, and rebel, and fight againſt him; 'tis by theſe that we break his Laws and violate his Commands; by theſe we affront his Goodneſs, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach his Name, diſparage his Word and Truth, and do the moſt we can to bring Religion it ſelf into Contempt. In ſhort, tho' it be in our Power to do Good, and to live like Men, yet we chuſe rather to abuſe his Creatures, till by ſo doing we debaſe our Nature, and become like unto the Beaſts that periſh.</p>
            <p>3 As God is our Maker and Preſerver,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:29495:21"/> ſo likewiſe is he the Founder of all our Happineſs. The Conſequence of which is, that there is no poſſible way for us to be happy without God. That both the thing it ſelf, and the way to it, and the qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations for it, are all from him: When we had loſt our Integrity, and had forfeited our Happineſs, even then God was pleaſed to have pity on us, and receive us again into Favour: And the better to encourage our Obedience, which is the Condition that he requires from us, he hath graciouſly Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to reward us with Eternal Life. So that it Concerns us all, as we deſire to be Happy, to underſtand our Duty, and to Practice it; to forſake our Sins, and amend our Ways: And in order to that, to curb our unruly Wills, to regulate our Paſſions, govern our Affections, and to ſubdue and mortifie our Luſts. In a word, we muſt endeavour ſo to change our corrupt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as to become better Men, and better Chriſtians too than I doubt moſt of us are. This is what we muſt all reſolve to do, becauſe the very Nature of Happineſs doth require it: But if we will try other Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riments, and will ſeek for Happineſs in our own way, we ſhall one day be convinc'd of our Miſtake, but then it will be too late to correct it: Which brings me to the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Thing I propoſed to make out, <hi>Viz.</hi> The groſs Abſurdity and unaccountable Folly of a wicked Life.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:29495:22"/>
            <p>II. Every vicious ungodly Perſon is liable to the imputation of Folly, and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he puts a notorious Cheat, a moſt ſhameful Abuſe upon himſelf. His whole deſign is to ſerve his Luſts, to humour and gratifie his Senſes: He makes no account at all of his better Part, nor ſhews any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the Dignity of his Nature: He conſiders not what is Proper and Neceſſary for him to do, but follows the motion of his Will, and the byaſs of his deprav'd In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination. He hath made a blind and wretched Choice, and is reſolv'd to purſue it, let the Iſſue and Conſequence be what it will. This is the way that the Wicked take, and <hi>this their way</hi> in the Pſalmiſt's Language <hi>is their Folly, Pſal.</hi> 49. 13. For ſince Religion was deſign'd to make Men firſt Good and then Happy, what greater Abſurdity can there be than to indulge cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Nature, and to place our Happineſs in that which is our Reproach and our Danger too?</p>
            <p>In the Account of the World, that Man is generally reputed a Fool, who Acts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his plain viſible Intereſts, and that only in temporal Matters, and the Affairs of this preſent Life. If he manages theſe untowardly, and to diſadvantage, there is no eſcaping the Cenſure of others: How much rather then is <hi>he</hi> to be accounted ſuch, who wilfully deceives himſelf, and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:29495:22"/> quite miſtakes his main Point, I mean the Happineſs and Salvation of his Soul.</p>
            <p>Hence it is that wicked Men are ſo oft in Scripture branded with the reproachful Name of <hi>Fool.</hi> In one place they are ſaid to be <hi>Children of Fools, viler than the Earth, Job</hi> 30. 8. The reaſon is, becauſe Sin by its tainting Quality doth debaſe them to the laſt degree of Vileneſs and Corruption. And elſewhere 'tis ſaid, <hi>Have all the workers of Iniquity no knowledge?</hi> No Judgment nor Conſideration of things? And again, <hi>Fools, becauſe of their Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, and becauſe of their Iniquities, are afflicted, Pſ.</hi> 107. 17. And <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us that <hi>'tis abomination to Fools to depart from Evil, Prov.</hi> 13. 19. In all which, and ſeveral other places, we are to underſtand by <hi>Fool,</hi> not the Idiot, but the Sinner; not the Natural, but the wilful Fool; one that Affects and Chuſes to be ſuch when he may be otherwiſe. In ſhort, 'tis the giddy, raſh, unthinking Perſon, he that ruſheth blindly on, and ſo conſidereth not in his Heart, neither is there Knowledge nor Underſtanding in his Head. It is this ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid ſenſeleſs ſort of Men, upon whom the wiſe Prophet beſtows this Character, <hi>They have not known, nor underſtood; they have ſhut their Eyes that they cannot ſee, and their Hearts that they cannot underſtand, Iſai.</hi> 44. 18. This is a miſerable State in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:29495:23"/> but then it is every Man's fault and reproach too, if he fall into it. For ſince Happineſs or Miſery is ſure to be our Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hereafter, accordingly as we demean our ſelves in this Life, what egregious Folly is it, if inſtead of purſuing our main Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, and that for which we came into the World, we only trifle away our time, or which is worſe, ſpend it in an idle fruitleſs courſe of Sin and Vanity.</p>
            <p>If we would act like Men and reaſonable Creatures, we muſt propoſe to our ſelves ſome End, which if attain'd to may be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to make us Happy. Now 'tis cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain nothing can ever make us ſo, but only the Service of God, and the Practice of Holineſs and Virtue. We may try other Experiments if we pleaſe, and ſo come to pay dear for our Folly at laſt: But that is the approv'd, certain, and only infallible way which never yet deceiv'd any Man. Reaſon, and Knowledge, and Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, are all on the ſide of Religion, and do all Recommend and Aſſert it. Religion is the beſt and moſt valuable Enjoyment of all other; 'tis the great Rule of our Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the chief Ornament and Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of our Nature. In a word, 'tis of that Importance to us in every Reſpect, that we can neither be Wiſe, nor Virtuous, nor Happy without it.</p>
            <p>Vain ſurely then are their pretences to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:29495:23"/> Wiſdom and Knowledge, who know not God, nor his Service, nor his Laws: For whatever elſe they may ſeem to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, yet if they are Ignorant or Regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs of theſe, they can never deſerve the title of <hi>Wiſe:</hi> For to be Wiſe is to be Religious, and conſequently whoever thinks to arrive at Wiſdom any other way, is ingag'd in a Miſtake, which will effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually prove him to be a Fool in the End. Again,</p>
            <p>2. Another Inſtance of the groſs Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and Folly of wicked Men, is that fond miſtaken Notion, which moſt of them have entertain'd of worldly and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual Delights! 'Tis here that their Hearts and Affections are ingag'd, 'tis here they expect to find not only their Eaſe but their Happineſs too. But what a ſhameful piece of ſelf-deceit are theſe Men Guilty of, and how wretchedly do they cheat and abuſe themſelves, while they purſue theſe Falſe Phantaſtical Pleaſures, theſe Imaginary Joys. While for the ſake of ſome beloved Sin, ſome boſom darling Luſt, they not only loſe all that peace and ſatisfaction of Mind, which is certainly to be found in the ways of Virtue, but moreover expoſe themſelves to the ſtings and upbraidings of a guilty Conſcience. Which whenever it is thoroughly awaken'd, as it will be one time or other, is ſure to vex and torment
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:29495:24"/> them: For then the Pleaſure, whatever it was, is vaniſh'd and gone, and there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains nothing but trouble and diſquiet, horrour and remorſe, which ſo gall and diſtract their Minds, that they know not which way to turn themſelves. None of their former Methods are now able to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert them; neither the Amuſements of Wit, nor the Charms of Wine, nor the Gaiety of Mirth, can entertain or relieve them. So true is that Obſervation which the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> makes, <hi>The wicked are like the troubled ſea when it cannot reſt, whoſe Waters caſt up mire and dirt: There is no Peace, ſaith my God, to the wicked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But beſide that inward regret and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh which Sinners create to themſelves, and which gives ſuch diſturbance to their Minds, how do they languiſh many times under bodily Pains and Diſeaſes; ſo that <hi>their bones are pierced in them in the Night-ſeaſon, and their Sinews take no reſt. Job</hi> 30. 17. As <hi>Job</hi> expreſſes it, Thus one Man drinks himſelf into a Fever or a Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, another is tortur'd with the Gout or Stone, and a Third pines a way of an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable Loathſom Diſtemper. Theſe are very often the Effects of a looſe and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular courſe of Life: But alas, ſo beſotted and ſenſeleſs are moſt wicked Men, that they never conſider the Conſequences of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:29495:24"/> their Actions: Whatever Inconveniencies they are like to endure, whether Poverty, or Diſgrace, or Sickneſs, or even Death it ſelf, they ſtill hug and careſs their Vices, and purſue their Debaucheries: They will not refrain their lewd intemperate Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, tho' thereby they break their Strength, and deſtroy their Health, and ruin their Conſtitution, ſo that at laſt whole troops of Diſeaſes ſeize upon them, and they go down with rottenneſs to the Grave.</p>
            <p>And now, all things conſider'd, is not this a fine diſcreet way of managing things? What! are theſe the marks and properties of Wiſdom, and are ſuch Men to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted the only refin'd and improv'd Wits of the Age? On the contrary, to ſpeak yet plainer, is it poſſible that ſuch Folly, or rather Madneſs as this is, ſhould paſs for Senſe and Reaſon and Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? Or that a Courſe of Life which is ſo Prejudicial both to Soul and Body, ſhould ever come to be ſo univerſally ingag'd in? And yet as unaccountable as the thing is, how many are there in the World, who tho' they live at this vile abominable Rate, are ſo far from thinking the worſe of themſelves for it, that they rather take a pride in being Extravagant, and Glory in being diſtinguiſh'd for their Vices. As if there was no Senſe but in ſinning, and no Reaſon like that of living like Beaſts.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:29495:25"/>
            <p>From what has been ſaid upon this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, 'tis, I hope, pretty plain that Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is the trueſt Wiſdom, and that Sin and Vice are nothing elſe but downright Ignorance and Folly. That wicked Men, as wiſe as they take themſelves to be, are all groſly miſtaken, that the Principles they proceed upon are Falſe and Groundleſs, and that their Practices are utterly incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the Dictates of right Reaſon, and the Laws of Sound and pure Religion. This is what I have endeavour'd to prove, tho' I am ſenſible when all is ſaid, wicked Men may ſtill plead in behalf of their Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and may deceive themſelves if they pleaſe, and too many I fear have ſo little Senſe as to do ſo: But yet when live as if there was no God, and do every thing in Contradiction to Reaſon as well as Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, ſurely then 'tis no hard Matter to prove them to be void of true Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>David</hi> I remember in one place hath this Expreſſion, <hi>The Lord looked down from Heaven upon the Children of Men, to ſee if there were any that did underſtand and ſeek God, Pſ.</hi> 14. 2. Which Words ſeem to Imply, that Wiſdom and true Piety, tho' they are different in Terms, are yet in Effect but one and the ſame thing: And Conſequently that none but good Men, and ſuch as <hi>ſeek</hi> or fear God
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:29495:25"/> and regard his Service, can in a proper Senſe be ſaid to <hi>Underſtand.</hi> The like was ſpoken alſo by <hi>Job</hi> long before. <hi>And unto Man he ſaid, the fear of the Lord, that is Wiſdom, and to depart from Evil is Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus I have ſhew'd at large the Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and the Folly of a ſinful courſe of Life. I come now in the <hi>Third</hi> place, to conſider the evil Conſequences which attend it with reſpect to Men's private Intereſts and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns.</p>
            <p>3. Great and manifold are the Miſchiefs which attend the practice of Sin and Vice, and ſo cloſe and conſtant is the attendance, that no Man thus ingag'd but is ſure to have a ſhare of them. To prove which I might appeal even to wicked Men them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, whether they have not experienc'd in ſome Meaſure, more or leſs, the ſad unhappy Conſequences which theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce: Whether the Sins and Enormities they are Guilty of, have not done them ſome real ſenſible Prejudice: Whether they have not either wounded their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, or blaſted their Credit, or brought ſome outward Calamity and Diſaſter upon them? 'Tis true indeed, ſome Sinners may and do eſcape better than other, becauſe the evils of this Life do not happen to all alike: Tho' ſome for their Sins do meet with quick and ſpeedy Diſappointments,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:29495:26"/> yet others are ſeen to flouriſh ſtill, and make a glorious ſhew, till at laſt ſome odd unlucky chance, ſome unexpected fatal ſtroke daſhes all their greatneſs in Pieces. When that happens, then is that Sentence of <hi>Zophar</hi> verified, <hi>Tho' his excellency mount up to the Heavens, and his Head reach unto the Clouds, yet they that have ſeen him ſhall ſay, where is he? The Eye alſo which ſaw him, ſhall ſee him no more, neither ſhall his Place any more behold him, Job</hi> 20. 6, 7, 9.</p>
            <p>Many and various are the Inſtances and Ways in which the evil Conſequences of vice Appear. I ſhall at preſent mention but theſe Three. 1. That of our <hi>Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</hi> 2. Our <hi>Eſtates.</hi> And, 3. Our <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Callings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. As to our Reputation in the World. That I Confeſs is a very true and tender Point, and moſt Men pretend to a more than ordinary Concern for it. Nay, there is hardly any Body ſo diſſolute, ſo void of all ſenſe of Honour or Virtue, but will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs ſome kind of Reſentment, ſome Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern at leaſt, whenever that is Attacqu'd or Queſtion'd. And yet were that in truth as dear to ſome Men as they ſay it is, certainly they would take more and better care of it than they do: Had they ſuch a deſire to be well thought of in the World, they would not ſurely expoſe themſelves to Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure:
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:29495:26"/> They would not tranſgreſs the rules of Decency, Modeſty and Sobriety, nor break in upon the Obligations of Truth and Juſtice: They would not Swear, and Curſe, and Blaſpheme, and be guilty of the vileſt Practices, as they too commonly are. Such Men perhaps may look great in their own Eyes, and fancy themſelves priviledg'd to do as they pleaſe: But ſtill while they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mean themſelves at this rate, are ſure to appear Contemptible to every Body elſe. For as the wiſe Man rightly obſerves, <hi>Who will Honour him that diſhonoureth his own Life?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many 'tis certain there are who will talk much and loud of their Reputation, and will aſſert it too ſometimes very unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly; but for all that are content to part with it almoſt at any Rate, and as if they were weary of keeping it, will Sacrifice it, to the next Temptation that comes in their way. Alas, ſo little regard have Men now-a-days to their Reputation, that they rather ſeem to put it to ſale, and for fear leſt they ſhould loſe their Market, are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to let it go at any Price: A ſmall ſum of Money, or a thin guſt of popular Breath, or any the moſt ſordid Vice, is able to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe it.</p>
            <p>Some again are very ſhy and reſerv'd in their outward Behaviour, and while they ſuſpect that others obſerve them, are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:29495:27"/> to take the leaſt ſtep amiſs: Theſe Men, the better to conceal their ill Deſigns, have put on a Mask of Piety, a Form of Godlineſs, but never conſider that ſuch Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifices, ſuch Diſguiſes do but render them ſtill more deform'd. The truth is, every Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy almoſt is aware of them, and knows their Practices, and hates to be impoſed on by fair Outſides, and ſpecious Pretences: Beſide that ſo odious, ſo deteſtable a Sin, is Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, that Religion it ſelf doth ſtill ſuffer on Account thereof.</p>
            <p>But whatever others do, let all of us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to maintain a clear Reputation, an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemiſh'd Character: 'Twill be of unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Advantage to us in moſt of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns and Duties of Converſation: Let us therefore cheriſh it with the greateſt tenderneſs and care, and let us ſtrive to eſtabliſh it, not by talking much of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, or pretending highly to it, but by the ſincere, conſtant and uniform Practice of it. Let our Zeal for God and his Service ſhine forth in all our Actions, let it appear bright, but not too glaring, for that is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times found to do rather Harm than Good. This is the only way to Preſerve or Increaſe a good Reputation where it is, and effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to retrieve it when it is unfortunately ſtain'd or loſt.</p>
            <p>Conſider again what a mean contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thing it is to be either Vicious or Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:29495:27"/> and what a grievous Scandal it brings to the Chriſtian Profeſſion: And therefore be careful to eſchew all manner of Evil, eſpecially the too common and faſhionable Vices and Corruptions of the Times, and not barely to eſchew, but as occaſion of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers to reprove them too. Diſcourage as much as in your lyes, all Profaneneſs and raſh Swearing, all kind of looſe, obſcene or atheiſtical Diſcourſe: Reject the entice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Luſt and Intemperance, and if at any time you are tempted thereto, ſay to your Acquaintance or Companions, as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> did on the like Occaſion, <hi>Depart from me, ye evil Doers, for I will keep the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of my God. I am a Companion of all them that fear him, and of them that keep his Precepts, Pſal. 119. 115. v.</hi> 63. But more eſpecially, as you value a good Name, a fair Reputation, take that friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Advice of his Son, <hi>Enter not into the Path of the wicked, and go not in the way of evil Men: Avoid it, paſs not by it, turn from it and paſs away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. In reſpect of our Eſtates. That Sin and Wickedneſs have a fatal Influence upon theſe is plain even to a Demonſtration. Sometimes a Curſe is entail'd upon our Poſſeſſions, which ſecretly deſcends to Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity; then it is that the Innocent but Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Inheritor can neither Enjoy that
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:29495:28"/> Wealth, nor ſecure that Inheritance, which at firſt was raiſed by Injuſtice or Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. But the miſchiefs of Prodigality are much more Senſible to us, we ſee plainly the many and great Inconveniences which attend that way: How Mens Follies and Extravagancies do prey upon their Eſtates, and make them moulder away ſo faſt, that nothing but Shame and Contempt is to be look'd for, and <hi>Poverty</hi> which <hi>comes</hi> upon them <hi>like an armed Man.</hi> This is the natural reſult of Luxury and Profuſeneſs, which are Sins now very rife and common amongſt us: The Conſequence of which has been and ſtill is the ruin of a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Families and Eſtates. But before I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs this Head, I cannot but take notice of one very common, but withal very miſchievous Cuſtom, and it is that of <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive and immoderate Gaming.</hi> Which as it is now-a-days practiſed by too many, is ſuch a fruitful complicated Evil, as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves to be ſeverely Cenſur'd by the Laws. However, all I ſhall move is, that if Men will not Conſider what they do, they may even thank themſelves for the Event; ſince they have nothing to complain of but their own vain Humour, their Careleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, their Vices and Impieties, which are of themſelves ſufficient to undo them, but oftentimes the Judgment of God ſtrikes in, and ſo makes their Miſery certain and unaviodable.</p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:29495:28"/>
            <p>3. In reſpect of our particular Callings. That Religion is highly ſerviceable to theſe Ends no Body can doubt, that will but conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what an immediate dependance theſe have upon the bleſſing of God, which is more than all the Care and Induſtry that Men can poſſible uſe. For except that ſecond and proſper their Endeavour, <hi>it is vain for them to riſe up early, and ſit up late, and eat the Bread of Sorrows, Pſal.</hi> 127. 2. In vain do they Project and Contrive to better their Fortune or increaſe their Store. So that if any ſuch Perſon be a bad Man, a looſe and careleſs Liver, unmindful of his Duty to God, and regardleſs of his Worſhip and Service, no wonder then if his Cuſtom fails, his Trade decays, and all, even his moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing Deſigns, miſcarry. For upon what Ground can ſuch a one expect to thrive, or look that any good Succeſs ſhould attend his Hopes and his Cares?</p>
            <p>If on the other Hand, to ſerve ſome lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Ends and Intereſts of his own, he takes up a Form of Godlineſs, and appears a Zealous and Devout Chriſtian, but at the ſame times does very ill Things, is perhaps a falſe and unjuſt Dealer, and makes no Conſcience to defraud and over-reach in Buying or Selling, that Man after all his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mureneſs is a groſs Hypocrite, a downright Knave. And if that <hi>his wickedneſs be ſweet in his Mouth,</hi> as <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaks, ſo that he will
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:29495:29"/> not repent of and forſake all ſuch diſhoneſt Practices, he will ſoon find to his Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row that he has indeed Cheated many, but his own Fooliſh wretched ſelf moſt of all.</p>
            <p>The Sum of what has been ſaid is this: That Irreligion and Vice are very perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious things, and do in their own Nature tend to the prejudice of Mens temporal Affairs: That 'tis for want of due Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration that Temptations gain upon them, and they are ſo often carried down the ſtream of bad Example: That 'tis a great Unhappineſs they do not ſee their Errour, and are not ſooner convinc'd of the Danger that awaits them: That were they once made ſenſible of that, they could not but Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn themſelves, and wonder how they came to be ſo miſtaken: That were they but ſo Wiſe as to Diſcern their true Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, they would quickly ſee the folly of Injuſtice and a wicked Life, and what a plain palpable Abſurdity it is to do any thing contrary to Truth, Reaſon, Honour or Conſcience.</p>
            <p>I might here go on to ſhew what farther Miſchiefs may and do Actually ariſe from a general Diſſoluteneſs and Depravation of Manners, particularly in the ordinary Buſineſs and common Tranſactions of Life. What a bad Influence it hath upon the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantag's of Society, and how apt it is to untie the Bands of Friendſhip, to deſtroy mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:29495:29"/> Fidelity, and conſequently to create Miſtruſts and Jealouſies among Men. For when they come to obſerve how little Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard is had to Religion, they preſently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, and with good reaſon too, that all things are running to Confuſion, and that no heed at all is to be given to what any Man ſays or declares, ſeem he ever ſo ſerious and reſerv'd.</p>
            <p>Indeed when all is done, 'tis Religion alone that makes Men fit to be truſted, 'tis that which breeds a generous Confidence, and which maintains a friendly Correſpondence between them; when therefore Wickedneſs doth ſo prevail, that neither Religion nor Conſcience is regarded, what Suſpicion and hard Cenſure is that like to produce? Where then is the Man whoſe Word will be taken, or whoſe Faith is to be relied upon: Nay, what Ground of Aſſurance can others have, but that after the faireſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, the moſt ſolemn Profeſſions, they may come to be deceiv'd by him at laſt? Theſe and many more Inconveniencies will unavoidably befal us, whilſt Impiety and Profaneneſs, and every other ſort of Vice is ſuffer'd to abound.</p>
            <p>I might likewiſe ſhew how our Sins and Vices tend directly to divide us, whether in Opinion or Affection, and conſequently do touch and wound us in the moſt ſenſible Part, I mean the Honour and Safety of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:29495:30"/> our Mother the Church, which is now ſo miſerably Torn and Rent in pieces by Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and Schiſm. But I ſhall wave this Argument, and proceed to ſhew in the <hi>Fourth</hi> and laſt Place,</p>
            <p>IV. How deſtructive Impiety is of the Welfare and Proſperity of any Nation or People.</p>
            <p>Now for the Proof of this particular Point, what need we any other Inſtance than that of the People in the Text, which is very Remarkable. God had Born long with that Stubborn, Diſobedient and Sinful People, but after all the Eſſays which he had made upon them for their Good, they ſtill continued to do wickedly, and <hi>walked in the Counſels and in the Imagination of their evil Heart.</hi> Great and Clamorous were their Sins, and ſuch as had Provok'd God to a juſt and a ſevere Reſentment? <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,</hi> ſaith he to the Prophet <hi>Jeremy, pray not thou for this People, neither lift up Cry nor Prayer for them, neither make Interceſſion to me, for I will not hear thee, Jer.</hi> 7. 16. God had now fix'd the date of their Calamity, ſo that no Interceſſion ſhould move him to avert it: He ſaw there was no likelihood at all of their Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and Amendment, and therefore he had determin'd to Chaſtiſe and Puniſh them to purpoſe: And to that end he rais'd up a potent Enemy againſt them, who with
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:29495:30"/> a mighty Force invaded their Country, ſeiz'd upon their Poſſeſſions, and carried the greater part of the Inhabitants away into Captivity: Of which Calamity and the Cauſe of it God himſelf aſſures them in a ſolemn manner, <hi>Hear, O Earth, behold, I will bring Evil upon this People, even the Fruit of their Thoughts, becauſe they have not hearken'd unto my Words, nor to my Law, but rejected it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>They have not hearken'd unto my Words, nor to my Law,</hi> ſaid God to the Impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent <hi>Jews:</hi> That was his Complaint and Charge againſt them, and that likewiſe was the ſole Cauſe of their Miſery and Deſolation. And now that God was thus Angry with his own People, and did ſo ſevery Puniſh them for their Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, have not other Nations, whoſe Sins and Iniquities abound, as much reaſon to fear the like Judgment and Severity? Yes, moſt undoubtedly: For do we not find that the ſame or like Sins and Provocations have ruin'd Cities, deſtroy'd Kingdoms, and laid waſte ſeveral Great and Flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Churches, even ſince the days of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity? Thus it hath far'd with thoſe falſe Chriſtians, thoſe unprofitable Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, thoſe ſlothful and wicked <hi>Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> who were long ſince caſt out as well as the <hi>Jews,</hi> and that becauſe they took not ſufficient Care of their Lord's Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:29495:31"/> 
               <hi>The Kingdom of God,</hi> as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour ſpeaks, <hi>hath been taken from them, and given to others that ſhould bring forth the Fruits thereof, Matt.</hi> 21. 43.</p>
            <p>Theſe and ſuch like Examples of Divine Vengeance are enough, one would think, to Startle us, if we have not loſt our Senſes, and to put us upon endeavouring a ſpeedy and thorough Reformation. That is the thing we want, and that which our Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances plainly require; and the rather, becauſe nothing but that can do us any Good, nothing but that can preſerve us from Evil. 'Tis not long, if we remember ſince our Fears were upon us, when God's Hand was lifted up, and the Stroke was juſt falling upon us: Then indeed we Sigh'd, and Mourn'd, and ſhew'd ſome Signs and Tokens of Amendment, but no ſooner was the Danger remov'd from us, but we preſently fell to our old Sins again, and ſoon became as Bad or Worſe than we were before. Surely to behave our ſelves thus after ſo great Mercy, is double Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and who can tell but that the Guilt of it is already put upon the Nation's ſcore?</p>
            <p>No Man certainly knows whether the Sins of this Nation be yet come to a Criſis, ſo as to be ripe for public Vengeance; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever thus much any Man may ſee, that 'tis high time to put a Stop to that Torrent
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:29495:31"/> of Wickedneſs which is breaking in upon us, and which nothing but a Diſcreet and and Reſolute Zeal is likely to Oppoſe. So that if we have any Kindneſs for our ſelves, or for thoſe that ſhall come after us, we muſt immediately reſolve upon other Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures: If we have any value for our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, our Government, our Liberties and Laws, we muſt do all we can to diſcoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance Impiety, and bring Vice to open Shame. As we deſire the Continuance of theſe our Enjoyments, which cannot but be dear to every one of us, we muſt be Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous in Promoting ſo Great, ſo Glorious, ſo neceſſary a Work. Which if we are Backward or Unwilling to Ingage in, let us conſider what the Conſequence of that Neglect muſt be, and what a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach it is we ſhould Live as we do, <hi>Quiet, and Secure, and Careleſs,</hi> of all that is Good? Like the Inhabitants of <hi>Laiſh,</hi> when, as 'tis ſaid, <hi>there was no Magiſtrate in the Land that might put them to Shame in any thing, Jud.</hi> 18. 7.</p>
            <p>We are Intent enough moſt of us upon the things of this World, Riches and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, and Pleaſures, and nothing can Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage us in the purſuit of them, but we commonly leave Religion to ſhift for it ſelf: That, 'tis plain, is the leaſt of our Care, unleſs it be to Wrangel and Diſpute about it, which oft-times we do to the Hurt
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:29495:32"/> and Reproach of it. The thing is very cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and all good Men are concern'd to ſee it, that the Intereſt of Religion declines daily amongſt us; but then where is the Fault and Misfortune of that to be charg'd? Is it not upon the Coldneſs of ſome, and the ill Lives of others, who Profeſs it? If we would in good Earneſt Secure or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the Welfare of Religion, the beſt way to do that is to practice it, and then we need not fear that either Popery or Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naticiſm will gain much Ground upon us. Let us therefore do ſomething for our own Safety, for the Honour of God, for the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Good, ſomething towards <hi>the healing of the Nation,</hi> that ſo God may be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil'd, our Sins pardon'd, and we become a Proſperous and Happy People.</p>
            <p>On the contrary, let us be aſſur'd that if we ſtill perſiſt in our Impieties, our good Things will all vaniſh and come to nothing: That very <hi>Liberty</hi> which we are ſo tender of, will become a ſnare to us, and will at laſt end in Slavery and Oppreſſion. Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how God threaten'd the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Prieſts, <hi>If he will not hear, and if ye will not lay it to Heart, to give Glory unto my Name, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, I will even ſend a Curſe upon you, and I will curſe your Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, Mat.</hi> 2. 2. In like manner, if we the ſinful People of this Land <hi>will not Hear, and if we will not lay it to Heart,</hi> ſo as to
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:29495:32"/> fear God, and give Glory to his Name by a ſincere and timely Repentance, then will he be Angry with us, and <hi>will curſe our Bleſſings</hi> alſo. All outward worldly Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts will then fly away, our Peace and our Plenty will both forſake us, and either ſome Foreign and Powerful Enemy will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade us, or elſe we ſhall fall out, and divide, and crumble in pieces amongſt our ſelves, ſo fatal an Aſpect hath Irreligion upon the Welfare and Proſperity of any People.</p>
            <p>To the End therefore that both Church and State may Continue and Flouriſh amongſt us, let us take care to amend our Lives, and Reform our Manners, that ſo God our great Benefactor may have no cauſe to complain of us, as having conferr'd ſo many Bleſſings and Mercies upon a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient and Unthankful People. That God hath of late appear'd ſo Eminently in our behalf, is a ſign that he hath a Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for us, and will ſtill Watch over us for good, if we by our Perverſeneſs do not force him upon other Methods. It is our part therefore ſo to Qualifie our ſelves as to be capable of his future Favours: <hi>He hath ſhewed us what is Good, and what he doth require of us,</hi> which is only <hi>to do juſtly, and to love Mercy, and to walk humbly with our God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude; I queſtion not but all ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber thinking Men will agree with me in
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:29495:33"/> this: That whereever it is that Atheiſm, Irreligion and Contempt of Godlineſs are ſeen, there nothing but Diſorder and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion is to be look'd for: On the other Hand, that whereſoever it is that Virtue is incourag'd, the Honour of God and of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion maintain'd, and every kind of Vice effectually diſcountenanc'd, there will the Divine Providence appear as a ſure Guard and invincible Security. There ſhall Peace, and Tranquility, and Abundance be found, and nothing ſhall interpoſe to Vex and Annoy. Not all the Power, nor all the Malice of the World, ſhall ever be able to Undermine that Society, Overturn that Government, or Deſtroy that Church which ſtands upon ſo firm a Foundation.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:29495:33"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
